咁誒？
嚇！咁點樣咧？
咁請胡志偉議員。
繼續，因為。
咁跟住咧就係誒。
誒，姚思榮議員提名本人。
啊，姚思榮議員，啊，梁美芬議員啦。
噉就誒，我接納提名啦。
有冇委員附議？陸仲雄議員附議。
誒，如果冇咧，噉就誒，我哋就而家可以正式。
好啦，噉啊，而家咧就想問下，有冇需要啊提名副主席？
我哋就先邀請香港律師會簡介兩項規則，然後請委員。
仲有冇人誒？應該要問係咯，因為我係獲提名啊嘛。你冇即係佢嘅意思，即係冇其他人。
主席一職嘅人選有效提名，需由一名委員口頭作出，並需由最少另外一名委員口頭附議，並為獲提名的委員接納。請委員提名。
誒噉，如果係咁咧，就誒本人接納提名啦。就誒，因為冇其他嘅誒議員係誒提名，噉我就誒自動當選咗本委員會嘅主席。
已經有足夠嘅法定人數，現在進行二零一九年律師專業釐常修訂規則及二零一九年律師專業釐常修訂第二號規則小組委員會主席嘅選舉，在於內務守則第二十二條及附錄四嘅選舉程序。現在請委員提名。
係。
yeah。
有冇？
welcome。
得就唔緊要。
係呢呢個講係嘛？
OK，好。
係咪佢啊？呢兩個咧？
Welcome all.
佢哋嘅代表進場未？
好，呀，welcome。
提名噉啊！請律師會。
Hello, good morning.
摩定係啊？邊個？定係納斯啊？
係咪進場啦？嚇，OK，噉我哋請Mr. Patrick。
我哋而家就請啊Mr.Nasir，啊，Yeah，welcome for you to express your view about the issue. Thank you.
你 need me to explain?
limited.
主席和成員。
with their practice.
Chair, morning.
The PLS covers all Hong Kong law firms.
And the indemnity calculation, and the second one is the professional indemnity amendment rules.
We administer the fund in accordance with Cap 159M of the Hong Kong Solicitors Indemnity Fund.
and the increase in the indemnity limit provided to law firms in general.
amendments to the rules. First is the solicitors' professional indemnity amendment rules relating to registered foreign lawyers.
through the through the company, which is which is a company limited by guarantee and established by the law society, for this particular purpose.
We're here today. I think you you have the Legislative Council brief before you. We have two.
details. Yeah, the as you can see, the compulsory indemnity insurance for solicitors was introduced in 1980, and the present one was introduced in 1989.
And pursuant to Rule Three One of solicitors professional indemnity rules, the Law Society authorises, establish and maintain the fund, which you do. And in general terms, the purpose of this fund is to provide indemnity against loss arising from claims in respect of any civil liability incurred by a solicitor in connection.
Between the firms.
The.
係。
I'll summarise instead of reading out.
jurisdictions are United States, England and mainland China.
Any PIS increase in the PIS contribution, it'll be borne by the fund itself.
Just explain to our members so that they can follow. So I'll summarise rather than read out the whole thing to save time, and then I'll leave more time for questions. You can see that the number of registered foreign lawyers have increased over the past fifteen years by one hundred and thirty-two percent.
and these areas of practice of the registered foreign lawyers encompasses a broad range from overseas listing of companies in the U.S. and claims may be brought against Hong Kong law firms for work done by registered foreign lawyers outside of Hong Kong.
seven reduction in contributions, except for one year, and they varied from think twice at fifty percent, and the rest at thirty three percent, and those figures are based on council's assessment of risk, based on the company's advice, which is in itself based on reports from experts.
Justification for introducing the amendments to the subsidiary legislation, particularly the RFL amendment rules, is the proposal was made with a view to a growing trend of Hong Kong law firms to employ registered foreign lawyers and the need to account for.
或註冊外國律師，作為資格成員的法務，律師，作為律師行的成員，相對於現有的規定，被視為無資格成員。因此，他們的風險暴露，到PIs可能被正確地反映在貢獻和扣除中。
And in view of the growing trend of solicitors and the expanding practices, cross-border practice arising from SEPA, it's anticipated the registered foreign lawyers will will increase and will continue to increase. In fact, as of thirty-one December two thousand and eighteen, the top three jurists
So in view of the growing potential exposure to the PIS scheme, against RFL's counsel, the Law Society has resolved to adopt recommendations of the board of the company to amend the PIS contribution formula and deductible calculations. So the RFLs employed by the Hong Kong law firms will be accounted for in the same manner.
unless I can.
畀額Further assistance.
That's ten million on top of the twenty million.
Foreign firms will have cover, which is equivalent to the cover that we're recommending.
Longer horizon before their cover bites, and therefore top-up cover would be more easy accessible even to the smaller firms, and therefore encourage further firms to take up top-up cover.
the rule six of the registered foreign lawyers also required registered foreign firms to take up cover, which is equivalent to the cover taken out by Hong Kong firms, and this will mean that registered foreign
That's the extent of my submissions. We're happy to take answers. Okay, thank you, Mr. Nasir.而家咧就係啊委員發問嘅時間。咁請問有冇啊委員要發問可以按鈕或者舉手嘅？
And for the the date of the rules should come in into effect on the first of July because that's the way that calculations are worked, and the PS indemnity limit would come into effect on the indemnity year, which is first October 2019.
As we do for consultants and solicitors in law firms, and the amendments may actually may result in more contributions being collected by the PS. However, the Council of the Law Society is empowered to reduce the amount of contributions, but that's usually done on the basis of actual reports, a proper analysis of.
the number of claims and reserves that we have at the end of each year, and then a report is made by the company to the council with the recommendations as to the risks and the level of risk, and the council then, depending on those reports, considers how much contribution. If you consider over the past seven years, we've had
As far as the indemnity limit is concerned, the present limit is ten million for each and every claim. It has been in place since one thousand, nine hundred and ninety four. After careful consideration, given the rise in property, given the claims that we have in the professional indemnity scheme, the financial position of the fund.
And the professional indemnity limits in overseas jurisdictions, we believe that 20 million per claim effective from 2019 is a prudent stance to take, as it will provide protection both to the public as well as firms. The increased limit of indemnity will not result in
Some smaller firms may not actually take out top-up cover, so this actually means that the cover now for them is 20 million. For the protection of the public, is 20 million as well. Those that take out cover, top-up cover, will also find it useful because now the top-up cover would have a
There's also an effect of the increase in the sense that section seven AD of the legal practitioners ordinance requires that the limited liability partnerships shall take out ten million cover on top of the minimum limits, which now means that limited liability partnerships will have a minimum cover of thirty million.
the the calculation meant is achieved by changing the factor for foreign lawyers and including them within consultants and solicitors. The rest of the formula remains the same, and in effect, that means that cover is increased.
Concern and litigants in person are always a matter of concern for legal representatives and and indeed the judges who sit in court.
to to put forward a case by themselves on a convincing matter, so I mean the concern is noted and I.
Hope you will take the assurance that we make every effort to make sure that litigants and persons are treated fairly, and so that they do understand what is being said in court.
誒買方嘅律師樓咧就好清楚咧，就將要求賣方係將已經收咗deposit咧係收翻走，畀翻嗰個買家。咁但係咧？
non-legalistic manner as is possible, because as I say, our panel do owe duties to the court as well as our indemnified firms. It's not an easy process, and we I think.
My experience is is that the courts are highly sympathetic to litigants in person and make strenuous efforts to make sure that the process is explained to them and understood and is operated fairly.
唔有完成嘅原因，因為係突然之間有一個嘅係賣賣方，原先個物業擁有人咧，佢係過身，咁變成一個遺產嘅probate，咁因為噉樣樣咪誒好簡單啦，cancel咗嗰個嗰個本嚟就cancel咗嗰個嘅係即係交易得㗎啦，咁但係咧。
In my direct experience, when we've had litigants who speak no English, for example, we have borne the cost of having every single document translated into Cantonese, and we've just we've done that as a matter of course to to facilitate the process.
係啊，第一位係胡志偉議員啊。多主席就我其實對於嗰個嘅賠償嘅準，即係個金額咧係上升咧，係冇大意見嘅，都相信係符合咗就係而家嗰個係咁多年嚟嘅通脹啊，各方面嘅條件。不過我想理解下咧，即係誒喺。
過往啦，誒呢一套嘅係專業離常嘅安排咧。第一就係即係有幾多嘅案例啦出現咗啦。咁第二個就係話，即係可唔可都講一講就係話一般或者平均嗰個嘅係即係離常嘅金額係幾多錢啦？咁同埋都想知道就係誒，因為我哋其實都遇過唔少嘅個案咧，係有爭議嘅，即係。
個客人同個律師樓嗰個工作之間嘅關係係有爭議嘅時間，可能覺得佢誒冇保障到嗰個係誒客户嘅權益嘅時候，咁究竟佢成個嘅係離上個機制咧，係通過一啲乜嘢嘅渠道咧去解決，同埋因為嗰個即係個客户咧就一般市民嚟嘅，佢亦都可能係冇。
冇呢個法律代表啦，去進行呢一方面，面對住呢一個嘅係即係誒律師樓嗰個誒喺爭議過程裏邊誒嗰個即係大家嗰個法律知識嘅係不平等嘅狀態。噉我都想知道喺呢一個部分裏邊個平衡點，可能律師公會係會點樣樣做咧，去達至到就係嗰個客人都。
都會喺佢嗰個申索嘅過程裏邊咧，係有充分嘅係即係支援畀到佢，令到個客人咧喺面對住呢一個即係法律知識上面又咁不對稱嘅處境裏邊咧，係仍然有個合理嘅安排。好啊，咁咧就因為咧而家我哋啊比較少嘅委員啊係。
舉手發言咧，我就會寬鬆少少嘅嚇。希望有興趣嘅佢可以啊繼續追問嘅議員，同埋我都要提醒委員啦。按議事規則第八十三A條嘅規定咧，如果委員就今次處理嘅事宜有任何直接或者間接金錢利益，應該喺發言之。
之前披露有關利益嘅性質咁咧，而家我哋胡志偉議員係誒提問噉，想請問律師會邊一位啊，或者係利常基金有限公司嘅代表邊一位係好Beyond啊誒誒，Yes, if I may take that from the indemnity fund. Um, understand the
From the indemnity fund's point of view, our our defendants, those the indemnified firms, are always represented by our panel solicitors, and they are in themselves also officers of the court. So if we have an unrepresented claimant, we make every effort to make sure that things are done in a most straightforward.
To be frank, from my direct experience, we don't have that many litigants in in in in person. Most of the claims made against SIF are conducted by by other other firms of of solicitors, mostly because they are or very often include conveyancing matters, and mostly people would struggle.
the process. Essentially, they need to take advice on whether there has been
喺個過程裏邊，律師樓咧就冇做好cancellations嗰個procedures，咁結果就而家hold住喺度啦，因為。
佢錢放咗畀人哋嘅時候咧，嗰一剎那已經做好一件事。噉我想問下啦，喺噉樣喺噉嘅過程裏邊，誒？
improper or negligent advice given by the firm that represented them. Now they can, they will have to do that by going to another firm of solicitors. But obviously they can do that.
呢啲法律援助可能佢未必係符合嘅，嘅點樣係令到佢哋係更加清楚？譬如好似消費者委員會，大家就知道啦。我消費我唔乜嘢，我就去消費者委員會啦。會喺個公眾上。
by seeking legal aid if if their assets come within that that those the categories yes so but from from our point of view from SIF's point of view what I would like to emphasise is that
嗰個即係你哋作為一個誒保護嘅屏障啦，畀佢哋去伸索嘅時候，誒會唔會係更加容易令到公眾去瞭解到嗰個程序咧？我諗應該係噉樣，同埋個過程係盡量令到公眾佢可以使用到嚇。
都會知道自己嘅權益咧，係係唔係可以通過呢個係即係誒誒誒誒離上保障嘅委員會咧，係去協助佢係申張，亦都令到咧係律師樓喺處理過程裏邊咧，亦都要更加謹慎咯。噉我想問下呢兩點，多謝主席。好，Yes，I mean，sorry。
誒，我唔好意思啊，主席，我我想可唔可以追問啊？好啊，嚇，第一我之前係問咗就係，不過我咁聽咗可能係冇乜case啦，其實個case唔係好多，可能主要都係律師樓同律師樓之間嘅爭議，我唔知係咪噉樣樣。咁誒，但係我喺呢一點上邊都想講翻，我諗我同你做咗好多唔同唔同嘅係社區工作嘅時間咧，都會遇。
到咧，即係誒，客户咧係覺得嗰個律師樓咧係冇好好代表到佢個權益，去即係保障佢應該有嘅權利噉樣樣嘅嚇。我我最我即係我我唔唔，我想攞個case去elaborate呢個point。譬如最近我哋遇到個case係即係誒買賣雙方有個交易唔能夠完成。
買家收咗錢，噉啊走拍下攞友，梗係唔理佢啦，係咪啊？咁揾唔到嗰個揾唔到嗰個嘅買家翻出嚟啦。咁但係咧個賣家就好慘啦。個賣家層樓就變咗就有一個嘅係即係登記停到登記，就話佢已經進入咗一個臨時買賣嘅合約。咁咁點咧噉樣樣咁？但係咧律師樓就話嗰個買。
代表買方嘅就話揾唔到嗰個買家啦。代表賣方嘅就話我搞唔到㗎啦，個買家唔理啊噉樣樣。跟住叫個叫個client自己去走去搞喎。即係我自己覺得聽落嘅時間咧就好明顯咧，係嗰個賣家嘅代表律師咧係冇做好佢自己嘅due diligence，係去確保就係。
嗰個客人咧，其實佢係應該通過一個乜嘢嘅渠道咧，係去尋找佢應該有嘅係即係公道啦。噉嘅第一點，第二個就係話，如果聽到係噉樣樣嘅事，其實呢個專業離常嘅係即係安排咧，似乎就冇經過一個比較上廣泛嘅宣傳咧，佢令到即係客人都。
Obviously, I can't comment on any specific matter, but I get the general gist of what you're saying. Is how do people know how to get reparation if they think they haven't been properly served by a solicitor? Obviously, hugely important question for the public. There is a law society website which is open to the public that may assist. It takes you through.
If such a claim is made against a solicitor, and on investigation, if it is clear to us that there was negligence in the performance of that solicitor's duties, then we will settle promptly. All right, we do not string out litigation. We will, in certain instances, settle before.
係，Mr. Nazir，yeah。
increase the pro bono work that we do.
好啊！仲有冇委員要發問？係周浩鼎議員。
individual who's aggrieved can always
and we have other functions where we deliver information about
within our website and other functions that we perform for the education of the public, as to the availability of legal services.
educate the public of the services available to the by solicitors. We also have pro bono services provided by law society members. We also have a telelaw service whereby they can call in and ask for information about specific areas of law.
想問一問咧，就係誒，由於佢嗰個公式係不變啦，當然係包咗註冊外地外地律師個M個數會變咗啦。咁但係咪除此之外，除咗呢個改動之外，基本上就再冇任何其他改動。如果比如話，舉個例。
或任何程序發出，如果它合適；如果程序發出，經過仔細顧慮，如果我們有責任，我們會盡快支付。所以，我希望這回答了你的問題。但係，無辦法繞過一個人在那種情況下。
會 simply have to take advice on whether the advice previously given was negligent。不過啊，我都幫手跟下阿胡志偉議員呢個問題，其實佢都係問得好好嘅，因為我哋誒一方面我哋自己都有法律背景啦嚇，我自己都係大律師啦，噉我哋嗰啲啊議員辦事處亦都會收好多呢啲。
求助個案咧，就係點咧？普通嘅人如果當佢咧係想投訴一個律師，佢已經好沮喪。你又要去再揾個另外一個律師，佢幫佢投訴另外一個律師。有時咧，佢有個信心嘅問題。第二，佢要畀錢，再要畀錢去律師，又去追究翻個律師。誒，喺市民嚟講咧。
就係好痛苦嘅。噉佢點解要揾議員咧？議員首先佢唔使又啊，佢又唔知會唔會一見面一個鐘又收幾多錢？佢已經係好唔滿意。譬如之前幫過佢嘅律師，咁所以喺即係我哋可能我我諗個問題咧，就係話你哋點樣面向公眾去知道或者去使用？
即係你哋係作為一個最後嘅一個誒堡壘，就係誒佢哋係誒百分百相信律師嘅。但係當律師可能喺某一個程度上令到佢哋係不滿意，甚至甚至失去咗信任嘅時候，啊，原來佢就會知道你哋呢一度咧，其實係誒係一個啊渠道。
而剛才阿誒Miss Stewart提到話：，喂係會睇下自己會唔會符合啲高A咧？噉我即係我咁估啫嚇。就算佢頭先剛才講嗰個案例，佢係買樓嘅，咁可能佢已經係冇可能符合嘅嚇。咁其實呢一類噉嘅所謂誒夾心階層，佢係肯定喺去去尋求。
I can't comment if I take this chair. I I can't comment on a specific case because we are regulator and therefore should not comment on specific cases. But in general, as far as the loss side is concerned, it does take very seriously any allegation of mis delivery of professional services. So the
call up the law society and make a complaint against the individual, on the issue of Fiona has already addressed the issue of indemnity cover. I will take this concern back to the council, but I may in relation to similar claims in the past, what we've done is we've incorporated it within our law week team.
The responsibilities of solicitors to their clients, and if we also have, as Fiona said, a website, and if you have suggestions as to what we should put on our website, we will of course do that. But I will as take it back to council the concerns raised in this chamber, and see how we can address specific issue.
yes.
啊！
甚至會參與部分嘅訴訟。
萬一齣現咗，畀人去索償。
咁如果係啊現時你知個，我哋又講緊大灣區。
係希望香港嘅誒律師佢擴展到內地嘅專業服務。
嗰個專業疏忽嘅時候咧，誒都係喺呢一個計劃嗰度可以包括嘅。
They will be covered under the PIS。嗯，即係我我係我好具體，因為而家其實講緊globalisation。
It's it's a little more nuanced in that there is no geographical exclusion under the rules.
我就有個問題想問啦，誒，我知道你哋都特別有關注到，即係律師行可能會係聘請一啲外地嘅律師啦。
誒係畀香港嘅律師，佢可以係用佢係普通法嘅嗰個誒法律專業嘅身份。
咁誒，當香港嘅律師樓喺誒，譬如喺內地嘅時候，啊，我舉就好具體嘅，譬如前海咧，佢就開始會開放。
香港 firms which operate outside the jurisdiction of Hong Kong may do so by means of representative offices, as long as the income that accrues from that representative office comes back to the Hong Kong firm.
喺適合嘅領域，可能係全部嘅訴訟。咁喺呢一方面嗰個啊，香港嘅律師喺呢一個專業離場嘅啊保障裏邊，係咪亦都包括埋喺裡面嘅咧？
In a proper way, and of course, see how we can address those concerns, which members of Letco usually do on a pro bono basis. But we do have a large pro bono group of lawyers, and in fact, we have awards each year which encourage lawyers to do more pro bono work, and we will try and.
誒唔該啊，主席。噉我自己身報我都係一個執業律師啦。咁因為喺本地律師行度有個執業律師嘅身份。誒，我想問一問咧，呢一個嘅誒今次呢個計劃咧，我見到因為畀我哋立法會嗰個參考文件咧，就特別提到咧，嗱今次嗰個誒將來嗰個誒誒補償嗰個賠償嘅金。
額去增加，我大家明嘅嚇，呢呢個我哋都明白，亦都誒同意嘅。咁但係咧，就唯一樣嘢，我想問咧，就係話喺畀我哋立法會嘅文件裏面咧，就曾經喺第十誒C個第十段就講到咧，修訂就可能會令到計劃收取較多嘅公款。咁但係咧。
根據專業離場守則，以下即係繼續講咧，就係律師會理事會咧可以獲授權扣減下一個離場期間嘅公款總款額。噉我亦都睇到咧，接下來誒嘅十三括弧十三段嗰度都講到咧，就係話計算律師行嘅專業離場公款嘅公式係維持不變嘅。噉我純粹。
作為好多本地嘅我哋中小型嘅律師行咧，誒可能佢未必有聘請到註冊外地律師嘅，可能冇嘅嚇。咁可唔可以咁講？就係話，對於呢啲本地嘅中小型嘅律師行喺今次嘅修訂計劃咧，或佢對佢嗰個誒整體嗰個公款嚟講係。
嗯。
市嘅嘅嘅計劃咁嚇，咁譬如呢一類。
And the Hong Kong entity is a Hong Kong law firm. Yes, absolutely. Yes.
cover, that's for the protection of the public. So we give a lot of risk management courses and other pro bono courses where we encourage lawyers to carry out pro bono work within.
未必會有咩改變，我咁理解會唔會都正確咧？嚇，想問一問啫，係唔該。Yes，the smaller firms will not have any effect on the contributions. Yes，they will get the benefit of the additional cover of the cost. Okay，明白。好，我我理清咗咁多嚟理解，唔該啊。好，仲有冇？誒噉。
yes，okay，that's that's the advantage of this scheme. It's very broad. In fact, that's also one of the risk factors in the sense that claims may be made from overseas, and therefore it's important to maintain a cautious level as the amount of fund that we keep。即係話佢哋去外國同埋去內地啊，其他司法管轄區。
全球化，所以我哋香港嘅律師行亦都可能聘請咗外國嘅律師，嗰個外國嘅律師又去翻佢本國嗰度，但係佢係係以呢間香港嘅律師行嘅外國嘅律師身份去，譬如幫啊印度嘅一個上。
都係全部包括曬㗎啦。只要佢係用，as as long as the entity which employs that person is is is not a business which is wholly conducted outside of Hong Kong, they will be covered. So in the scenario where you where you're saying that the RFL is still employed by the Hong Kong entity, then that would that
好誒咁誒，跟住落嚟係阿容海欣議員係係主席誒。其實我我自己係大律師嚟嘅，咁冇呢個直接關係啦。即係喺呢個professional indemnity嘅方面，我自己大律師係要自己誒去買一個保險啦。咁誒，但係咧有好多嘅事務律師咧有。
有同我哋反映過，例如佢哋做一啲誒pro bono work，即係響誒幫社會做或者響議員辦事處度做，響街頭度做一啲嘅誒畀誒市民嘅一啲法律意見。噉佢哋都擔心咧，即係自己個誒保險咧，其實包唔包括佢哋響街頭？
樓道做或者係唔係響自己律師樓道畀一啲嘅法律意見？噉我哋自己大律師就係自己更新㗎啦，即係自己幾時畀一啲意見都係自己要要承擔翻個責任。但係律師咧，佢哋因為如果佢哋唔係響自己個公司或者唔係響誒cost of work入邊provide呢啲service嘅話，噉佢哋呢？
一個誒專業嚟上呢一個修訂規則咧，其實包唔包括佢哋誒嗰一啲嘅工作類別，包括埋誒一啲嘅誒義務嘅法律意見啊，義務嘅法律工作啊噉樣，或者畀市民嘅意見。咁其實好多律師都有反映過呢個反意見畀我，即係佢哋自己都擔心啊，究竟我可？
可唔可以響誒議員辦事處度畀一啲誒法律意見咧？幫幫一啲議員或者係響市民喺街頭上面畀啲意見畀市民咧，佢哋擔心。但係我覺得，如果誒律師公會律師會咧係想自己啲會員係畀多啲呢啲專業服務畀市民咧，我覺得應該係做多啲呢方面嘅宣。
services of our firm.
first of all， we encourage them to carry out pro bono work.
行咧行家咧，就係我哋係會講明呢一個，佢唔係用一個專業律師嘅身份。
嗱，第有有幾樣嘢嘅，我諗有一啲咧係需要你哋可能協助推動嘅，有一啲可能亦都要啊，要令到啊。
They get authority to do so. Any advice they give thereafter will be protected by the indemnity provided by the PIS. the the fees is not the issue. It's the fact that the work must emanate from the firm.
then we encourage them to hold a practising certificate, seek an exemption from the law side which they entitled to under Rule Seven of this list of professional indemnity rules, but also to take out insurance cover, and in fact we have.
我知啊！如果你收咗一蚊，可能你就算收得咁平，你進入咗一個嗰個係誒客户或者專業嘅關係。咁呢個可能係可以提醒下啊嗰啲願意做公眾服務嘅誒誒誒同行啦，亦都好多嘅呢啲係好值得欣賞嘅。
啊！又或者佢講talk嘅時候，佢唔係嚇。我第一佢唔係去用緊一個專業嗰個身份，我講talk。咁呢啲咧，可能誒亦都舉辦或者誒大家誒負責嘅呢個呢呢呢呢啲安排嘅，大家會要有呢一個基本上嘅認識。
傳同埋教育，令到佢哋係知道自己個責任係去到邊度。噉我想釐清翻今次即係呢一個規則係唔係包括埋誒呢啲唔係響自己個職項範圍上面嘅嘅工作。噉我想問下律師會嘅意見，唔該。係請，Mr. Lawson，please。We actually
Our rules provide that so long as the fees inure to the firm, then that individual who is providing pro bono services within the ambit of the firm under the name of the firm, whether inside the firm or outside, is provided cover. But if the individual is carrying out giving out legal advice, not
Not within the firm, but outside, say to an NGO, then of course there is no cover. The law side has looked at this through the pro bono services, and it's had many risk management courses and other courses for solicitors where we guide members that if they're going to do that outside, then it is safer for.
them to keep a practising certificate and then seek an exemption from the law society, because our rules are such that you cannot practise as a solicitor unless you have insurance cover, and if you don't have insurance cover, then you you're not you're not acting as a solicitor. If you hold yourself out as a solicitor, you must have insurance.
the confines of their law firm, so that there can be proper conflict checks, there can be proper record kept, and they can have cover to protect both the solicitor and a member of the public who they are advising on a pro bono basis. Of course, if they choose to go on their individual basis outside of the law firm.
Arrange for insurance cover, which you know, if we can explain on that additional cover, or Ming can explain the additional cover that we've arranged for those. I don't think it's in place. It's not. It's still under discussion. It's it's not in place. So we've actually tried to arrange for insurance cover to be taken out by members if they want to do it outside, and we've also
also arrange the risk of taking out insurance cover on your own, which is that you need to have runoff cover. If you're going to advise somebody, then that person may come back to you after three years or later. Of course, as you know, and they need to maintain runoff cover. So we always advise our members that.
and we also advise them that they should carry our pro bono work within the law firm so that the public and the individual is protected, because we have a very good system. even when the solicitor retires, unlike other jurisdictions or other agreements, that solicitor can rest at peace and say that he has got cover even if he.
嗯。
Client A and the
誒，請兩位可以都回應下，啊，Mr. Nasir同埋Miss Stewart，啊。
That client's a employee may go out, and of course, as as you know, there's no need for me to explain that. So, conflicts is a key issue that may prevent law firms from
嘅公司或者係律師會，佢去對待呢一類嘅誒，我哋自己嘅會員嘅公眾服務嘅時候，係啊好容易好輕省，差唔多好似係一個notification噉就得咧嚇。
噉嘅嗰個保險池係闊啲，噉佢一個人去買佢又要闊啲喎。咁呢啲會唔會係話啊好平嘅？係因為鼓勵，因為我哋成日都話公眾係需要呢啲專業嘅協助，但係同時誒，我哋亦都要保障嗰個專業嘅。
有幾位嘅律師朋友，佢係一路十年嚟都係願意做呢樣嘢嘅。噉佢當年佢如果做到嗰個身份喺個律師樓，佢自己已經係包括到啦。佢係啊合夥人或者根本關關律師樓，佢整體都係好願意佢嘅員工做公益嘅。
retires or the firm closes, so yes, we encourage pro bono work, but we encourage them to do it within the protection of the solicitor's professional indemnity. This is quite easy for solicitors to protect themselves. Say if they're giving advice to a clinic, all they simply need to do is go to the partner of their firm and say, I wish to provide this. I wish to do it under the auspices.
嗯嗱，我我喺呢一個問題，我都想補充嘅，因為咧呢啲我哋都過去啊，未做議員都做好多啦。我喺成大教法律嘅時候，亦都好多市民直情係上到嚟，佢知道你係啊大律師，佢亦都會問你，或者甚至係誒關於誒唔同嘅管轄區嘅法律。
嗰個誒願意服務公眾嘅，即係進行公職公益誒事務嘅誒律師本人咧，亦都可能要誒意識。噉我諗我哋誒以往不嬲都會係提醒誒嚟幫我哋做誒義務法律諮詢嘅同學。
係有埋書有個誒書面大家知道，佢係攞一個法律嘅諮詢，呢個唔會係啊佢亦都唔係用一個誒需要係誒去到一個律師行，即係唔係提供緊一個專業服務，即係even誒一蚊我亦都唔會收嘅，我哋自己法律行。
誒第二咧，我諗係需要你哋去協助推動嘅。誒，剛才頭先Mr.納斯一講嗰個咧，我就好欣賞。我希望特委可以喺呢一度今日開完呢個會，你回去可以協助誒推動啦。就係嗰個所謂誒律師會，佢願意畀嗰個豁免啦。
exception嚇原因咧就係事情未必好似阿Miss Stewart諗得咁容易咧，一個可能好年青嘅律師，佢又要向佢嘅律師行叫佢律師行去負責埋佢喺出面嘅，有時亦都係佢自己嘅公眾嘅參與，咁誒佢。
會多咗一個程序去做，又又律師行去負責佢喺出邊嘅誒義務服務，唔係間間律師樓佢會願意係咁做嘅。咁所以咧誒，我覺得呢個係一個商户更加需要嘅。當然，如果有一啲人佢係特別積極添嘅，譬如我有十年有一位有。
噉就係有一啲情況，就係佢買保險嘅話，假設嚇，我中意自由啲，我唔係好中意我間律師行知道我自己工作之後，我係幫乜嘢人或者點樣去做嘅。噉佢可能啊，我穩陣啲，我費事煩，我去買個保險。咁可能就需要保險嗰度會唔會呢一類係啊？
嗯，特別平咧，即係除咗佢申請攞嗰個嗯豁免之外，咁所以呢個係要可能你哋去協助推動，係誒。如果佢真係話要去個人去買保險係嘛？律師樓如果你成十幾個到一百個以上嗰啲，佢平好多㗎嘛，你一定係。
嘅。
係，咪啊？
係做呢個決定咧，兩個問題，多主席。係。
And as I said previously, if the advice is that they were, then we will.
is alleged to have happened, and they then by using established legal principles advise us whether in fact the solicitors were negligent or not.
所以到你個問題，係咪 cheaper？如果你有100個個體，yes，但係佢哋佢哋係組織咗呢100個個體，係，
人士、專業朋友，佢唔會因為我做公公共嘅事務而無端惹上一啲好繁瑣嘅嘢。可能最後佢唔會有事，不過好煩啫。大家已經付出噉嘅時間啦，咁噉你哋會唔會亦都可以啊？承諾喺誒去推動，無論係誒保險。
Well, on a on a policy, I can't give an undertaking, but I can certainly bring this back to council for them to discuss. We have law week, we also have the president's letter. How the firms deal with it is a is a question very much depend on factors such as conflict. The firm may have established.
Either giving a general agreement to lawyers to go out, and because there has to be a certain amount of conflict check if the lawyer is going to do that. But apart from that, we do encourage lawyers individually and firms to assist in pro bono, taking into account their own commercial interests and of course their conflict interests and professional.
Conduct rules. We can of course continue with our efforts to promote pro bono work. Our president has done that and our pro bono committee has done that. On the insurance issue, Fiona, do you have anything? Yeah. Yes. I mean, this chimes with your earlier point. We obviously need to do better at communicating what is available.
And Mr Nazir has already promised that he will take that back to the council on this and the earlier point, which we which we will do. I would like to assure you that the issue of pro bono cover is also quite a high priority at the moment within the law society, and we are looking at ways of perhaps providing a master policy for individuals.
我我我理解嘅，我理解Mr. Nassir提提過幾次係law week。
啊，lawic，我哋其實都有啊，好好高度嘅讚讚賞啦。但係咧，嗰個咧，似乎喺公眾成個公眾嘅角度，始終係法律界嘅人啦，包括下法律嘅學生啦，或者我哋啊法律嘅教授啦，係會啊好清楚。不過你話從公眾嘅角度，佢最容易咧。
佢真係會去揾啲議員啦，誒揾啲誒佢熟悉嘅誒民間嘅機構。咁呢一度咧，的確近年嚟係好嘅。我覺得多咗年青嘅律師，佢係肯幫嘅。咁所以我哋亦都睇下點樣可以令到佢哋更加安心啦。做公眾服務嘅時候，好跟住我哋有兩位嘅追問嘅誒，胡志偉議員。
好，多謝主席。我我好簡單，我其實想請教下咧，喺個賠償，當然有個係賠償金額嘅定定嗰個issue啦。咁有兩個可能性，第一可能佢通過訴訟之後咧，去揾到佢嗰個嘅係即係所謂經濟損失啦。咁然後有個法庭嘅判決，咁可能我理解就會係翻翻去，如果
真係係發覺係呢一個律師樓嘅呢句賬數嘅話，噉就會自然就有嗰個離場基金嗰度咧係賠償。我唔知有冇理解錯啦嚇呢第一點，或者可能係甚至就係如果係誒係係咪律係可能律師樓要先作賠償，然後賠唔夠嘅時間咧先至再補埋條數上去。咁呢個第一個情況，即係個金額點樣定定同埋。
中間嗰個即係誒律師樓，如果佢有疏忽嘅話，咁其實佢自己嘅責任係點樣樣係去去判斷咧？噉樣樣咁咧，第一個第二個就係如果佢唔經過呢個litigation，純粹就係話即係誒同嗰個嘅係solicitor之間有個dispute嘅話，咁又點樣樣係去作出一個判斷？
段咧係即係點樣樣嘅賠點樣嘅賠償嘅金額咧，先至合情理咧噉樣樣。咁呢一度係咪有一個嘅係即係法律嘅依據，即係話誒賠償保險基金嗰邊咧係佢係已經係有一個final and即係final and full嘅係decision嘅power咧？
Right, Miss Stewart. Yes, certainly. Yes, so there are certain number of questions within that. Let me try and deal with them each by each. When a claim is made against a firm of solicitors, we appoint our own panel solicitors to advise us on what happened. Right. So they make a careful investigation.
settle as soon as we possibly can, which brings me to your next question: how do you decide on the quantum? Again, it will depend on the type of case. But if it's a conveyancing transaction, it may be the loss of value of an apartment. If it's a breach of contract, it may be damages which flow from that.
Does that make clear?
好清楚，好跟住落嚟就係周浩鼎議員，係。
and then I think your last question was can SIF decide the quantum?
no， we come to a view on what we think is the appropriate and reasonable level of of of compensation for any any claim.
If we can't negotiate, then we may, if necessary, proceed to court and let the judge decide. We may concede liability and simply argue about quantum and let the judge come come to a view.
fact that whatever we pay out, that firm is then claims loaded upon. So it's you know it's obviously in the claimant's interest to get as much as possible, but from the defendant's point of view, they don't want to pay out any more than the proper amount of damages as as assessed.
breach of contract, but again we are given advice by our panel on the established legal principles what the appropriate quantum is. Now obviously there is often a discrepancy between what we think the quantum is and what the plaintiff or the claimant thinks, and then that becomes a matter of negotiation.
The indemnity firm has to agree with us, all right. The the indemnity scheme is very much a partnership between the indemnity scheme and the solicitors. So both the firm and the company has to agree one that the claim should be settled and two at what the appropriate level is. Because we are very mindful of the.
好，即係簡單講，就佢一定要係得到誒誒誒申索人同埋呢一個被申索者兩個大家都agree on嗰個誒理上嗰個金額，先至會達至嘅結果。如果唔係嘅話，就仍然都要擺翻上court度make個final decisions。係，am I right？OK，OK，Yes，correct。佢哋聽得好。
誒唔該，主席。誒我就想跟進少少關於頭先嗰個義務法律服務提供嗰個情況嘅。咁誒，事實上咧，而家我哋見到有唔少我哋執業律師嘅行家咧，誒對於喺啊外面去提供一啲義務法律服務咧，佢哋係遇到一啲嘅困難。個困難就正如頭先阿主席所，
我講咧，第一啊，理論上佢應該係要得到佢嗰個服務嘅律師樓嘅同意，即係呢一個服務係應該係呢個律師行嘅業務範圍內去做呢個嘅誒業務嘅服務，噉就可以包含喺嗰個專業理上嘅保障裏面啦。咁但係往往咧，作為一啲律師樓嘅。
啊啊！擁有者啦嚇，噉佢哋即係可能就係我諗得。如果好簡單就係哇，點解我仲要為你喺一個僱員喺外面去提供啲義務嘅法律顧問嘅服務嘅情況下，就意見去提供當中咧，再要額外提供一啲補償咧？萬一有咩事就真係好似我哋啲律師。
樓嘅擁有人就會咩飛啦噉，咁嗰啲律師樓嘅擁有人咧，好多時都有呢種概念嘅。噉我亦都聽到頭先，我慶幸聽到咧，就係話誒，剛才都提到關於如果提供呢啲業務嘅法律服務咧，係有一個所謂嘅保險嘅安排。咁當然，正如啊頭先啊主。
所講啦，而家你哋都翻去檢視緊，睇下會唔會將嗰個嘅收個保費咧，可以儘量平一啲嗱。呢個好重要嘅，因為點解咧？如果佢要選擇自己出去啊，為咗呢啲義務嘅法律諮詢或者義務嘅法律意見嘅提供，去買份保險咧，如果你個價碼低咧，佢就願意咁做。
嘅，即係或者佢都佢樂意，但係如果一旦咧個金額太高咧，就令到人會卻步，因為亦都咁講咧，誒唔係間間律師樓嘅大老細都覺得可以願意為自己嘅員工咧去孭飛，即係覺得你去做義務法律服務，你去做社區服務冇問題，但係你要我。
我喺我哋嗰份買嘅專業保險嘅補償裏面，要包埋你咧，噉啊羊毛出住羊身上，有咩事起上嚟就真係我哋間friend孭飛嘅，咁所以變咗嚟講咧，真係遇到有少少呢啲困難，噉我希望即係律師會可能今日聽咗咧，或者或者講多少少畀我哋聽，目前你哋考慮喺檢視。
to try and achieve.
And I know a lot of.
rather than during the daytime.
young persons do that, but they do it in the evening.
但，我們正在尋找一個解決方案，讓我們能夠在這個領域
So there's a number of factors that have to be balanced in order for a young person to achieve.
We try to achieve it, but also I think, in addition to the law firms, it's not just a firm. A law firm.
任何 legal practice, because of the professional conduct rules, has to bear in mind these additional factors, which are non-commercial, more professional rules.
The insurers need to be able to assess what the risk is. I mean, what what is are all these individuals giving advice on? You know, what are the potential claims that could arise? So
younger lawyers who want to go and do the work can do it in the evenings, and you know those who do pro bono work take out time from their own personal time to go and do this work.
啊嘅正正啊，Mr. Nassau講咗一個就係好現實嘅問題啦。你哋誒剛才提嘅咧比較多就係話啊，會唔會係同嗰個律師樓嘅客户嘅利益可能有利益衝突？噉我相信咧，其實所有專業嘅律師應該係好清楚呢一點嘅。
而嗰個幫誒呢啲義務嘅法律服務買嗰份保險，你哋會大概點出嚟？係咪真係會可能有一啲平啲嘅價格可以推進到你哋嘅方向？係咪都咁咧？我想了解多少少啫。唔該，主席。好啊，誒，Mr. Stewart，we we obviously this will become completely a matter of commercial negotiation in the in the in the insurance。
A body, it could be either the government or the law society, purchases a master policy, which would then cover every individual engaged in pro bono work outside the auspices of their firm. It's easy to say, quite hard to put into practice, which is why we're we're still looking at it.
Whilst the Law Society completely wants to support and encourage people to do this, insurers are not so civic-minded and they are not they're not out to give us cheap rates. They will price the risk as they think fit. And again, that's one of the problems because when you have a lot of people across different organisations.
It is a slightly complicated process, but that is the solution that we are we are working, we're trying to achieve. Given that there won't be any data, yes, insurers will price it at a risk that they can take on. So it's a very difficult formula in the insurance market.
所以，many law firms don't mind that. What they do want is to protect the young lawyer by making sure they take a note, they make sure they do the conflict check so that they don't, you know, conflict themselves out of work that they may be doing or other members of their firm may be doing. So actually, it's a bit more than just money. So a law firm having to run
反為係咧誒，我會考慮到係所謂嘅誒，佢可能係有參政自由啊。佢可能係唔一定有一啲嘅誒，佢想幫嘅機構又未必同佢嗰個誒老闆係一樣嘅。咁所以呢個係屬於佢私人嘅一個，佢想幫佢選擇幫咩團體嘅一個空間嚟嘅。
係。
好，跟住就係阿胡志。
都冇法去孭起嘅時間，噉係會有啲咩機制協助處理咧？
啲舊區舊區重建嘅過程咧，就往往如果係中間嗰個地盤嘅買賣唔係做到back to back嘅話咧，好容易就變成就係即係新買咗地盤嘅業主咧。
Anyway, not not within the auspices of the professional indemnity scheme. As a statutory scheme, we are authorised only to pay any single claim up to the amount in the rules. So I'm afraid any claim, presently over 10 million.
所以我我同意嘅嚇，意思即係話其實我哋有一個叫離場保險，另一個誒呢個當然係自己誒呢一個離場基金啦。噉嘅意思就係話律師樓自己可能仲要賣自己再賣另外一個嘅係即係誒誒誒誒誒top up top up嘅係即係market嘅保險係嘛？O K明白。
佢亦都未必係想誒誒誒同嗰個律師行嘅老闆講，又或者佢同佢講都未必得到批准。咁所以，我哋係要容許一個佢已經係誒執業律師嘅成員，佢有噉嘅選擇，佢中意幫，譬如話幫邊個政黨，幫邊個政團，佢自己去選擇嘅，佢未必需要畀。
佢嘅律師樓，佢知道呢個係佢嘅私人嘅一個活動嘅空間。咁所以當佢係選擇去自己去買呢個保險，即係反為嗰個衝突，我覺得唔係喺嗰啲經濟或者客户嗰度，而係佢係想保持呢一個空間嘅時候咧。誒，我所以我就係回到頭先嗰點，我哋無論佢係。
係點解？誒，佢自己嘅選擇，佢幫呢個機構去幫呢個民間團體嘅時候，佢要嗰要買保險，佢係我希望係一個非常平而係一啲即係好平嘅誒學家，佢係可以付出得到。我甚至當然話可以係誒豁免就最好啦，係嘛噉。但係你。
你係要點樣去做點facilitate呢樣嘢嚇？咁呢個咧係一個好現實嘅，而而家喺呢個誒誒，現在經常其實大家就會係係用個人自己就去處理，唔使煩啊嘛。有時唔想畀啲老闆知道㗎，老闆最好你啊，夜晚黑休息下，第二日再。
佢精神啲噉，佢但係佢願意付出嘅時間，佢去再參參參加一啲公務誒，就係噉嘅情況嚇。噉我覺得呢個亦都咧應該係仲有一個會唔會亦都畀嗰個成即係嗰個會員佢係亦都有一定嘅誒私隱咧？即係我我唔知道喺嗰個list佢係。
啊，notify咗嗰個律師會嘅時候，佢有啲好後生嘅，佢暫時未想畀人知道我幫邊個團體嘅，有啲係噉嘅嚇嘅時候，又會唔會去可以有噉嘅空間咧？除咗買保險之外，嚇呢啲係我覺得我哋係應該幫嘅，我哋覺得佢哋係有噉嘅自由嚇，係去去享有嘅自由嚟嘅。
惠爾。多謝主席，我我我最後一個問題又緊要嚇。誒，頭先牽涉到contem嘅問題啦。咁誒，因為我過往都做過只case咧，就聽收嗰個喺嗰個court嘅litigation裏邊咧，個結果就係個solicitor咧係被判咧有negligence嘅，而個賠償嗰個contem係好大嘅，大到就係話個。
私樓咧，就算佢block咗都好啦，即係佢claim自己bankrupt都好啦，都即係搞唔掂條數。噉我理解，當然個尾數就可能係由呢一個嘅係誒賠償基金嗰度咧係協助客户啦。咁但係我想問下，係咪止此為止嘅啫嚇？因為如果真係個金額好大嘅時候，譬如我哋係牽
佢唔會履行喺舊嗰間公司所承諾嘅東西，咁令到就係話咧，當其時賣咗出去嘅小買一樓出去嘅小業主咧，佢最後咧就好大損失嘅。咁所以我想問下就係呢個利上誒，第一我見銀買二千萬啦，咁但係即係假設出嚟嘅contem大到就係個律師留自己。
We cannot help, though that's where top-up insurance comes in, and obviously we encourage all firms to take out top-up insurance in the commercial market. If if Legco approves our proposal, then from the 1st of October we will be able to contribute up to 20 million any any one claim. So that's that's a big improvement.
yes.
to make clear that they are added.
I'm working off a slightly different copy to you, but hopefully it's all right. So.
嗰個附屬法例一百五十九章《律師專業離常規則》。
The second amendment is immediately underneath to the definition of indemnity.
And again, the amendment is simply the addition of the words any, a foreign lawyer.
of making a clarification that foreign lawyers are indemnified under the scheme.
咁誒，首先就喺嗰個誒適宜係係咪由法律顧問去介紹咧？
誒律師會介紹好啊嚇誒，你哋邊一位會係介紹係？I I'll take you through the amendments. Sure.
委員拆息咧，因為內務委員會主席本來咧就係作出預告，想喺四月十七號立法會嘅會議上咧，就係動議將呢一個條例嘅修訂規則。
誒係嗰個審議期延展到五月廿二號嘅，不過因為該次嘅立法會會議冇辦法處理呢兩項延展，咁結果呢兩項嘅規則。
correct，保障自己做大啲嘅嘅項目嚇。OK，誒，如果我哋喺基本上嗰個誒大嘅原則，大家意見不大咧，我哋就係跟住落嚟就會係去到嗰個誒草案委員會嘅嚇。咁誒嗰個草案裡面。
啦，噉我亦都順便宣佈先啦，因為咧，我哋根據我哋一貫嘅做法咧，我哋都會係誒會邀請公眾人士或者相關團體，佢就兩項規則表達意見，咁可以喺誒互聯網啊各方面，我哋擺上去大家表達意見。誒，但係咧就請。
嘅提出嘅期限咧，其實就已經係過咗噉，所以其實我哋咧就可以表達意見，但係咧就誒唔可以咧再有具體提出修訂。但係咧，我都希望大家咧呢一個真係牽涉到公眾嘅，尤其是我哋請到律師會嘅負責。
喺度啦。咁如果我哋表達咗嘅意見，誒有啲係未必需要去到提修訂嘅，但係希望你哋都會聽拎翻去咧，同佢哋商討。譬如我哋剛才提出嘅咁咧，呢個咧都係亦都公眾咧係希望我哋係問大家嘅。好啦，咁跟住咧，我哋就誒首先睇一。
The very first amendment is found in the interpretation section of the rules, and it's a change to the definition of indemnified. Obviously, a key definition within the rules, and the amendment here is simply to add the words any foreign lawyer. So this is just the implementation.
呀。
我們已經花費不少時間討論這個。
好冇？咁跟住誒，繼續嚇，continue please。
provides that upon the issue of a receipt, indemnity is provided.
啲修補嘅時候，我哋注意呢一點，特別係律政司嗰邊都可以係注意一下。
That means that the indemnified must be able to show evidence of a receipt issued to the firm.
The next amendment is found to rule 10, which is headed the entitlement to indemnity, and in sub-paragraph 2.
now that's usually pretty straightforward, but it is possible for a retired solicitor or even a perhaps a retired solicitor.
And the specific amendment here, again, is simply to add in foreign lawyers, so that it is quite clear that they also, if they work for a firm that is no longer in existence, nonetheless they are still entitled to indemnity.
This may need a little bit of background information. The this is the key in what you would call in commercial insurance terms, the key insurance clause. So it sets out the entitlement to indemnity. Rule 10, sub para 1.
係，我有個technical issue in relation to the proposed amendments to the definition of indemnity. Because the original definitions reads as follows: indemnity means the indemnity to which the indemnified or a former solicitor is entitled under Rule Ten. So that's fine because both the indemnified and a former solicitor
律師是單數名詞，所以用is entitled是正確。但現在修訂案有加進一堆其他的人，到定義裡，包括他們的法定和法律代表，這是複數名詞。所以我想問，是否繼續用is entitled是正確的語法？
And I think we all feel slightly embarrassed that we are not grammatical expert enough. All I can say in our defence is that this is the version that the DOJ approved, and they are very expert in drafting. We have no issues with is or are. We think the meaning and intention of the provision is clear.
如果那係一個清晰嘅偏好，我哋會高興地修改佢。喺啊，我諗誒誒好多謝法律顧問。噉我哋盡量應該法律咧係完善一啲嘅嚇，唔好有啊文法上嘅錯誤。噉啊，我諗下次有機會再作一。
for his previous firm to be no longer in existence, in which case he cannot show a receipt. So rule ten, sub paragraph little two, deals with those situations where a solicitor cannot access a receipt, and it makes it clear that they are nonetheless entitled to indemnity.
The next sub paragraph three, I can take you through those rules if you wish. But essentially, the the import of that paragraph is simply again to make it quite clear that all the salient rules, all the terms and conditions of the rules apply to those.
who。
第。
所以。
The foreign lawyers to make sure that.
Next amendment is to schedule one.
have indemnity and we have added in there.
They get the benefit, but also they have to follow the rules. So it's quid pro quo.
under sub paragraph one little A， where the definition of M
These rules proposed to commence on the 1st of July. Right, certainly it's it's slightly technical, but I'll do my best.
the the basis on which we will make our preliminary assessment of contribution will be based on the quarterly return which has been filed on the 30th of June.
所以， as you can see from that provision, when we calculate the contribution, we do so with the information as at the thirty first of July.
The firms are obliged to provide on a quarterly basis all the information about the composition of their firm, so the partners, the assistants and now the foreign lawyers. So
是changed to include foreign lawyers. So whereas previously we would count the number of partners and then the assistant solicitors, we now count the number of foreign lawyers too.好，我哋請法律顧問。
But remember that when we make a basic contribution on renewal each year, we are always doing on the basis of the previous year's information, and therefore it is always adjusted at the next indemnity period.
And that is paragraph one, obligation to make contributions. And again, it is simply addition of foreign lawyers, so that they are now added in when we are looking at contributions. And that is made clear in the amendment to paragraph two, calculation of contribution.
In relation to amendments to the formula for calculating contributions, now I understand that for M now includes foreign lawyers as at thirty one st of July immediately preceding such intended period. Can you explain why, if thirty one st of July is the essential date, why are
冇計。
有冇？
then it's the same for everybody.
我 hope that's is slightly the same dull.
That's why we pick the first of July to make sure that it all dovetails, and that when we recalculate a whole year later.
them the additional time to sort of perhaps ring us up and clarify what what what what they need need to do. So that's your second question. The first question, the definition of in
咧噉我都想誒問清楚一啲，咁同埋另外一樣嘢我都瞭解咧。嗱，因為而家劃線就係二零一九年七月一號之後就開始用噉嘅安排啊嘛，噉啊都睇到咧，就係裡面有曾經睇過就係話誒。
indemnity is is is as you said is to make it as as as broad as possible. There are various ways people can be employed. I might be thinking of locums. We want to provide protection to firms and the public as broadly as we can.
Okay， continue please。Thank you。Thank you very much. Then the next amendment is found also in Schedule One。等等等等，唔好意思，wait。啊，周浩鼎議員有一啲議題。係係。啊，唔該啊，主席。啊，就有一個問題想請教翻嘅，因為頭先一路解釋咧嗰個離常嘅定義啦，嗱。
今次睇翻幾個誒條文裏面咧，都講得好清楚。誒獲利上者同嗰個利上定義，亦都係除咗外地嘅外國律師之外咧，亦都包含埋誒曾受僱於啊或者從事該執業業務嘅，無論係助理律師啊顧問。
嗯，實習律師或者其他嘅僱員都包埋㗎嘛嚇，即係呢個安排係新嘅。今次一個傳播嗱，我就想問一問咧，誒嗰個所謂嘅誒，如果係僱員或者即係因為我見你哋寫所謂其他人嗱，因為讀即係就照讀嘅。我睇翻中文咧就係，不論是助理律師、外地律師。
顧問、實習律師或其他人，即係呢個或其他人。我想問清楚係咪即係我哋firm裏邊嗰啲，例如啲Power Legal啊，啊，即係呢啲係啦。呢種就算係屬於受僱人員嘅嗰個誒誒誒嘅範圍裡面咧，即係或者係個範圍究竟係包邊啲？
將來咧，如果你有啲咩新嘅喐動，即係個律師樓裏面嗰個改動變動咧，當然要報翻啦。咁但係係唔係每一次都係誒新嘅一份保險嚟嘅時候先至報啊？定還是係你有任何改變嘅時候都應該要誒即時報？因為平時我哋如果law society咧，我哋知道咧一喐動就應。
應該盡快報嘅噉，我唔知道而家呢個安排新嘅金治離上計劃係咪應該都係一喐動噉，照樣都係同你哋報翻咧噉啊？問一問清楚呢個兩兩個問題，唔該。Yes, I'll start with the second question first, if I may. Yes, so that's an additional efficacy of administration is also another reason for the first.
As you know, the firms are obliged to provide their gross fee income and the details by August the fifteenth. So we would like to give them as much time as possible. We understand this as a change. In our experience, firms often make mistakes in the quarterly returns. We would like to give
我哋，we can't we can't anticipate the way solicitors organise themselves. They're very clever coming up with new ways of employing people。阿周，係頂意係誒一句啫。我我理解嘅，即係點解我咁問咧？只不過因為誒，老實講，其實如果比較大型嘅律師行噉，佢嘅僱員人數眾多。
呀。
誒。
little two。
subparagraph little three A.
The next amendment is to.
Yes, that's correct. Okay，噉我哋繼續落啦，好冇嚇。
The next amendment is to schedule one paragraph two.
我哋掌握到噉就得㗎啦。我我想知道就係最緊要，你頭先都講，我見到都係比較松嘅，即即係包就包曬。噉我覺得噉就容易啲理解嘅嚇。唔該。
Sorry, little three underneath is a grammatical amendment, particular of the name and position because it's a it's a singular. So that one we did get right.
人員嘅，咁嗰啲只要佢哋係執行緊嗰間律師行，畀佢嘅誒指示，從而中間可能牽涉到喺呢啲索償裏邊，咁都係會包括啦，係咪應該咁講咧？嚇。
difficult to try and cover everyone, so the otherwise is cover that and the possibility of change of terminology. Okay. Okay.誒，我可唔可以講我嘅理解，即係話嗱，譬如你就算係實習生，總之係嗰佢做嘅嘢係嗰個法律師行。
And this is for our administrative purposes, because you'll appreciate that since we are now rating registered foreign lawyers, we need to track. So we need to track within firms, we need to track the date of employments. So this paragraph gives us the authority to ask for those particulars.
咁可能有啲人係palligo嘅身份，有啲人未必係。咁但係誒，如果我按照頭先嘅理解咧，睇嚟都係包曬嘅，即係即係即係可以包含到嘅。噉我覺得咁都安全嘅嚇，即係即係如果你寫鬆啲噉，咪總之即係由於你個金額而家都已經提升到二千萬啦，噉我覺得都係係比較容易處理嘅。噉我。
講一句係，Mr. Nasir。The larger firms and more foreign firms, the way that is in the old times, a solicitor, consultant or partner. But now with larger firms, they come from different jurisdictions. They have different terminologies like counsel or general counsel or other terminologies, and that would then be.
總之係會承擔嘅嘢嚇，當然唔係超越律師行授權佢哋可以做嘅嘢嚇。可能佢自己嗰啲就係另外要另外嘅法律責任啦。咁亦都可能有啲部門誒係佢哋嘅人事管理或者又有技術啊好多㗎嘛。大嘅律師行仲有好多其他。
So I'm now looking at the amendment to Schedule 1, paragraph 2, little 3, sorry, little B, little 1, and that simply states how we calculate the contribution, and that is a straightforward amendment by the addition of the words foreign lawyers, paragraph.
first.
seven or seventeen.
對唔住，可以慢。
操把十月一號。
$ in respect of any one claim.
Little B, little C.
會有，一個 entitlement of 20 million。
However, all claims made after the 1st of October 19.
Yes, sorry. Shall I repeat what I said? Would that be helpful? Yeah. So this we're in Schedule One.
的咁多啊！你係去到三係嘛？三A。Sorry。Yes。
Prior to the 1st of October 2019, the enactment date will remain at a limit of 10 million in respect of any one claim.
呢個等我對下中文先。點解中文？Yes, on my version of the rules, it's at page 17. But your page is 17.
Yes，the the the new paragraphs are labelled CAPA and CAPA。我都希望啊啊，你哋可以誒諒解，我哋咧就係中英文一齊睇。
Paragraph two, sub-paragraph little B, sub-paragraph little C, and these two are the first amendments. Was introduce the increased limit of liability, which will come into force on the 1st of October.
which it reads for the purposes of sub paragraph claims page during such period shall not include, and then this is the first of the amendments that deals with the increase of the indemnity limit, so it's split into two sections and all claims made.
我哋要睇埋嗰個中文版，睇下佢啱唔啱，就即係所以咧，有時我哋會睇多咗一倍嘅時間對一對個中文嘅嚇，咁所以你可以稍為再慢少少。頭先十月一號嗰，Certainly yes嚇。
D。
three。
And then it's.
little。
two three。
O.K.， sorry。
所以，噉樣，咁
You are talking about schedule one.
呀！對，因為。
三D.數字數字編號是真係好複雜，我幫你查下，係段落。
The RFL, sorry, yeah, yeah, should be paragraph 3D of schedule one.
If if a firm had a dispute about how many consultants and assistants they had, and they wanted to take issue with it, then it has to go to the council for for their final finding.
Oh, you you you you you're taking us through both sets of rules together. Yeah, I didn't realise. Yeah, so that's why we that's the confusion. Yes, sorry. I thought I would just go through. So we're talking about rules number two now. Okay, okay, all right.
It should be the same, right? It's law. Sure. In that case, the next amendment for the RFL amendments is found to Schedule One, Paragraph Three, headed 'Decisions by the Council'. Yes. Are we? Yeah.
Because rather than go and then come back, but I'm happy to do it either whichever way you want. How would you prefer to do? It would be needed to go through each one separately. Okay, all right, yeah, because we we have to go through every procedure and we have to guarantee the Chinese translation. Okay, at least it's not deviating too.
Decisions by the council. Okay, three small D, right? Subsection D. Okay, that is only a small amendment. Solicitors, yes, to foreign lawyers and solicitors. Okay. So that's just as it was. Yes, and to give you the general background, that some decisions are reserved to the council, and obviously.
好。
你點睇？
然後，The Next。
Too fast or next one?
Yeah, it's an addition.
Tell us when you're ready.
other than the deductible.
We'll wait for you to tell us when we should come in.
係你，yes，所以explain that，yeah。
Okay， and and the next one should be schedule three。
Paragraph three, two, C. C. Correct, yep.
entitled to the full limit of indemnity.
this makes it clear that a former employee is also
所以它 starts if a person other than a former solicitor, so we're not dealing with former solicitors. So any other former employees, and
three. next one is three headed, and this is simply an amendment to the heading of that paragraph to make it clear what what it's talking about.
二二C。二二，That's correct. And again, that is the addition of the word foreign lawyers, and to make it clear that, for the benefit of getting their cover, they are also liable to pay a deductible of fifteen thousand dollars per per claim. Okay.
哈哈。
And that.
Two.
Paragraph。
See, see, little, yes.
會被 entitled to the limit of indemnity.
takes us back to schedule one.
We will go back now and track through the amendments in relation to the increase in the indemnity limit.
Thank you. Noted, and that I think is the end of the end of the RFL amendments. So.
C A, capital letter A, six little C, yes, with the new paragraphs capital A and capital A A B, yeah, so.
Okay, to move to the next one. Yes, yep. The next amendment on the limit is found in Schedule Three, Paragraph Two, headed the determination of limit of indemnity.
This obviously sets out quite clearly that the limit of indemnity will change for all claims after, on or after the first of October 2019.
詞噉，但係中文就就咁男人他噉，其實如果可以用該人或者that person咁噉就解決咗呢個問題啦。不過呢個不過呢個唔影響嗰個意思嘅嚇。英文佢O K喎，英文佢係he or she喎，所以係中文嘅問題。
或者英文都可以用that person，會咁咁更加更加中性啦。That person係咪？He or she，嚇，he or she就我哋都都都O K嘅，佢cover㗎啦嚇。但係嗰個中文就第二日可以注意一下啦嚇，第二日可以再注意下，即係我哋。But it doesn't really affect the meaning of the。係啦嚇，OK。
啊哈，OK，誒，翻嚟中文。Just a very minor drafting point. But I better do do it in Chinese，因為It concerns concerns the Chinese text。呢一度咧，因為而家律政司咧就通常用用呢啲比較誒性性別中性嘅嘅嘅措詞方法啦。咁呢度其實個C段咧係講落嘅誒。
誒指一啲物，任何曾受僱於或從事於執與執業涉誒執業業務有關工作嘅人嘅情況咁人啦。咁睇下邊咧就用一他咁其實其實我都比可能比較誒性別中中性嘅話咧，可能會用該人會好好啲。因為如果你係分英文咧，佢係用he or
翻譯。
嗯。
即係中文。
每筆其實本來應該係咪？
呢個anyone claim？
咁即係係係咪誒？
因為你呢一度中文咧，就係講不超過該筆。
咁其實係咪中文係咪應該話每一筆啊？本來。
其實應該本來噉就會更加誒好嘅。
佢因為佢係好emphasize嗰個anyone claim係周浩鼎議員。
The any one claim is important because if there is more than one claim, more than one deductible is payable. Okay.
And as we've seen in the previous amendments, registered foreign lawyers will have to pay a deductible if a claim is made against them.
即係其實係咪可本來係可以就咁用any claim咧？定係呢個any one係指誒每一筆？
我可唔可以問下少少嗰個應該係冇分別嘅係嘛？你嗰個英文your English is any one claim。
And this makes it clear that the the new limit is still nevertheless subject and to the deductible. In other words, it is inclusive of the deductible.
係法律顧問。我諗中文，因為我唔係中文專家。不過咁中中文有冇個一字？我諗到個個意思都係一樣。每就係每就係即係every啦。係啦，本來係應該誒，以不超過每一筆。
yeah。
你呢度係話佢係？
係咪其實？
And this deals with former solicitors.
open bracket two open bracket little A
即係佢一開，佢咪有個問題，就係呢個一千萬。
係由你哋嗰度獲得索償，係咪就係解？其實解答咗佢嗰個問題。
Hi. So the next amendment for the limit of liability is Schedule 3, paragraph 3.
And again, this is simply the amendation of the limit for former solicitors. Again, with that same distinction as claims made pre and post the first of October two thousand and nineteen.
喺二零一九年嘅十月一號或之後去commence咧，噉就可以有個新rule supply啦。我咁理解正唔正確？係係正確係嘛？OK OK That's fine. Thank you。得。噉我哋繼續啦。
O.K.呢個係咪即係都可以係去翻？就係剛才阿胡志偉議員問嗰個問題，就係佢哋係自己誒唔夠啦，噉就去到你哋嗰度個差額。
誒唔該，主席，我我一個少少問題，即係clarify一下嘅啫。因為我睇到咧誒誒嗰個二號規則嘅三A B啱啱提到嗰度咧，我就想嗱，我照讀一讀出嚟啊。就所有在二零一九年十月一日或之後首次向有權獲
提供離常嘅人提出的申索而言啊，就任何一宗申索而支付的超過二千萬嘅任何款額，我我純粹想問下咧，呢個十月一號呢個劃線咧，誒，因為如果我睇中文噉就咁理解咧，就係二零一九年嘅十月一號之後，任何提出嘅。
搜索就有新嘅rules嚟apply啦。咁但係即係，如果嗰個人本身個negligence嘅情況係發生喺兩年之前嘅，即係我嘅理解就係話，總之如果兩可能一一年前或者兩年前啊發生咗一個negligence之後未喐，去到二零一九年嘅十月二號，當係咁講咧，就開始comment。
呢個legal proceeding，然後就有呢個新rule supply。我個理解係噉啊，就唔係話要你個negligence都要係喺二零一九年嘅十月一號以後發生，噉你之後先claim咧，先至係算數。而係你即係總之，你係嗰個negligence發生喺任何之前嘅時間，但係你個legal action只要
得唔得㗎？
超出。
一嗰部分。
係嘛？他需就他超出。
係咪可以任嗰個律師行去揀咧？
誒數額係低過一千萬啦，譬如咁講，或者誒。
列出嘅款額，但不超過B部分列出嘅有關款額。
Yes, it's slightly complex the drafting of the rules generally, but in this paragraph, what what it's actually saying is that this is the limit that you are entitled to.
如果佢哋要畀人啊，新索嘅。
即係譬如佢係只係被申索五百萬，噉佢就用咗你哋呢嚿錢嚟賠先。佢自己都會買保險㗎，即係正如頭先講，你有啲數額係好大㗎嘛。
可能係講緊幾十億，噉佢又再買其他，咁但係可能呢個新索額有一單case個嗰嗰筆嗰個claim，即係個新索係細額啲，佢就claim你哋嗰度算啦，咁得唔得？
噉佢就揀，佢係可以揀喺你哋嗰度攞咗，即係嗰個索償先，就唔用自己嗰個。佢通常都有自己買保險，大家top top up㗎嘛。你嗰個其實係一個保險池嚟㗎嘛。
此修訂簡單增加限額，但係受同限額一樣的免責額，而且值得留意，雖然限額增加，免責額唔係。而免責額對企業仍保持在20萬，所以。
你可唔可以詳細少少？因為呢度你係就講咧，你改成咧就係與一千萬之間嘅差額為上眼嘅損失部分而獲得利上，可唔可以解釋清楚少少呢個二細A？
等佢答，嚇，等佢答，等佢答，等佢答。Yes， we will pay first. We we we we never ask members to put their hand in their own pocket to pay claims. We we pay first until it is not enough. Until we have spent 10 million essentially. As soon as we spent 10 million, we have to stop. And then and then they need to top up. Okay.
subject to the payment of your deductible, and you see in little B below it sets out the deductibles which will apply to a former a former solicitor in various scenarios, i.e. whether he was a sole practitioner or whether he was an assistant solicitor. There are different different deductibles payable. So this.
Alright.
O.K.
呢個係咪一樣？
跟住。
amendment. okay.
就係另外一個啦。
一樣嘅係嘛？O.K.
And I think that's the last.
好，咁跟住就係下一個嘅修訂，係。
誒相關嘅，噉我哋都希望律師會啊，係拎翻去參考啦，就誒以備下次再有機會修訂嘅時候，就再做好啲啦。
好咁咧就誒，我哋咧其實都基本上誒順利完成咗。咁剛才其實誒法律顧問同埋我提出嘅一啲問題咧。
咁誒，如果法律顧問仲有冇其他補充？各位委員，如果冇嘅咧，我就係可以係誒要問各位委員誒，我哋係會。
所以，The next amendment is in the paragraph underneath C, and again, that's it's the same amendment to be clarifying that for former employees, that that is the entitlement subject to deductibles.
結束呢個委員會嘅工作係等埋嗰啲嘅意見一齊嚇，就會加埋嗰啲意見之後咧，就會向盡快向內務委員會提交報告。咁如果大家冇其他嘅意見，我就宣佈會議結束。多謝大家，多謝。
都係誒同呢一個誒可能文法啊或者翻譯嗰度有關嘅噉啊，律政司冇代表喺度啦。咁但係咧就我都希望誒律師會啦，因為呢一個誒將來你哋係記錄在案啦。咁將來可能又都要有機會再。
我要誒更新修訂呢一個嘅條例嘅時候咧，就將佢係誒加翻落去，補充翻做得誒完美一啲噉樣，好冇？噉我剛才講過咧，我哋就誒會係邀請公眾人士嘅意見啦。誒嗰啲意見亦都如果係誒。
真夠啊，發到。